Guide to the Washington Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Washington family papers
1751-1870
MS 538
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3.25
The collection contains correspondence and other papers of President George Washington, Martha Dandridge Washington, and William Augustine Washington, half brother of George Washington.
Washington family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of various donors between 1929 and 1948.
Scope and Contents
The Washington Family Papers consists of correspondence and other papers of George Washington and various members of his family, in particular Martha (Dandridge) Washington and William Augustine Washington, half-brother of George. Letters from Alexander Hamilton, Nathaniel Greene, and George Clinton are also included. The bulk of the material relates to George and Martha Washington. As well as correspondence there are military papers and personal financial papers. Most of these items are photostatic copies or facsimiles; the few originals have been removed in the interests of security.
Other materials included in the papers are a number of ledgers belonging to William Augustine Washington and others, and several engraved portraits of George Washington dating from the 1800s.
These papers were given to Yale University by various donors over the period 1929 to 1948.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Families; Southern States; United States -- History -- 1783-1815; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; United States -- Politics and government; Presidents; Ashton, Burdett -- 1747-1814; Beverley, Robert; Greene, Nathanael, 1742-1786; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804; Harper, Robert Goodloe, 1765-1825; Washington, George, 1732-1799; Washington, Martha, 1731-1802; Washington, William, 1752-1810; Washington family
- Inventory, 1751-1870; .75 linear feet (2 boxes, 1 folio)
  - Ashton, Burdett (1747-1814):
    - ALS from Thomas Douglas, 1777 December 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Account of sales in the estate of his mother-in-law, Anne (Ayelett) Washington (Mrs. Augustus, Jr.), 1774-1775 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Beverley, Robert, Jr.: Ledger of personal and farm accounts, "Blandfield," Essex County, Virginia, 1791-1803 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Clinton, George (1739-1812): Draft letter to George Washington, 1778 October 28
    General note
    See: box 1, folder 7
  - Greene, Nathaniel (1742-1786): ALS to his wife, [ca. 1780 October 14] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hamilton, Alexander (1757-1804):
    - ALS to Andrew Ward, 1777 March 14
    - AN to George Washington, [ca. 1794]
      See: box 1, folder 14
  - Harper, Robert Goodloe (1765-1825): ALS to Oliver Wolcott, 1804 January 23 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Trumbull, Jonathan, Jr. (1740-1809): Discharge papers of Isaac Wilsey and Brister Baker; signed also by George Washington, 1783 June 4, 8
    General
  - Washington, George (1732-1799):
    - Correspondence:
      - ALS to Robert Dinwiddie, 1753 October 17 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - ALS to Moses Child, 1775 November 24 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - ALS to the Secret Committee of the New York legislature, 1776 July 21 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - 3 ALS to Lund Washington, 1776 October 6, December 10, 17 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        See also: box 3
      - ALS to Andrew Ward; ALS from Alexander Hamilton to Ward on verso, 1777 March 14 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - ALS to Elisha Boudinot, 1777 March 29 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - ALS to James M. Varnum, 1777 November 4 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - ALS to Henry Lee (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - ALS to George Clinton; draft reply from Clinton on verso, 1778 October 24 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - ALS to John Sullivan, 1779 October 8 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Facsimile to commander of French fleet, 1780 September 12 (Box 1, Folder 7A)
      - ALS to George Mason, 1780 October 22 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - ALS to William Greene, 1781 January 5 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - ALS to George Clinton, 1781 April 7 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - ALS to Lund Washington, 1782 January 8 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - ALS to Henry Knox, 1787 March 8 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - ALS to Jonathan Edwards, Jr., 1788 August 28 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - 2 ALS to John Lewis, 1791 August 8, 1792 July 20 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - ALS to John Francis Mercer, 1792 July 23 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - ALS to Burwell Bassett, 1793 March 4 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - AL to Dr. Anderson, 1794 May 26 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - ALS to Alexander Spotswood, 1794 November 23 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - ALS to William Pearce, 1796 August 19 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - ALS to James McHenry, 1798 May 6 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - ALS to the Grand Lodge of Pennsylvania (facsimile), undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Autograph, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Other papers:
      - Survey map made in Frederick County, Virginia, 1751 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Memorandum re: ownership of land known as "Northern Neck;" valuation of this land by jurors on verso, [1752?]; 1762, November 27 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Commission from Continental Congress, 1775 June 19
        See: box 3
      - Ledger (facsimile), 1775 June - 1783 June (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - "Plan of manoevres to be executed before Maj-Genl Gates at West Point" (not by G. W.), [post-1776] (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Discharge papers of Isaac Wilsey and Brister Baker; signed also by Jonathan Trumbull, Jr., 1783 July 4, 8 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Notes: "From Post Vincennes to the Mouth of the Wabash,", [ca. 1793] (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Notes concerning a farm; AN from Alexander Hamilton on verso, [ca. 1794] (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Certificate of appointment of Solomon Porter as inspector of revenue, Hartford, 1795 August 24
      - Memorandum re: Secretary at War Wilkenson, 1796 May 17 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - "Sundries Bought on Account of A. W.,", 1796 June 6 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - "Memorandum of Stock in the banks of Alexandria and Columbia,", [1796?] (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Note re: shrubbery, 1797 April 7 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Notes re: farms, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Printed matter: Engraved portraits, with texts of Washington's Farewell Address and the Declaration of Independence, [ca. 1820-1870] (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Washington, Martha (1732-1802):
    - ALS to a member of the family of Nathaniel Greene, 1797 March 3 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - ALS to Mrs. Fitzsimmons, 1797 April 30 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - ALS to Mrs. Powell, 1797 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - ALS to Mrs. Elizabeth Powell, 1797 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Washington, William Augustine (1757-1810):
    - Ledger of personal and farm accounts, 1779-1783 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - "Memorandum Book, containing notes & memorandums of his Transactions for the Estate of Colo. Thomas Turner,", 1787-1795 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - "Index to Ledger B," estate of Thomas Turner, [1787?] (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - "Accts & Transactions of the Executors [W. A. Washington and Burdett Ashton] of Richard Henry Lee, decd,", 1793-1796 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Inventory and record of the settlement of the estate of W. A. Washington, by Robert Beverley, Jr., 1810-1813 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Oversize (Folio) (Box 3)